[Music]
Great, so Ethereum in 30 minutes.
This is a presentation I've given
at basically every Devcon since launch.
What's interesting is
how Ethereum the ecosystem evolves,
how Ethereum the protocol evolves,
and how the times change,
so the contents keep changing
quite a bit. If you go back to the
2015 version, you'll hear
a lot about uncle blocks. Uncle
blocks were a Proof of Work (PoW) feature,
but now we have proof of stake (PoS), so we
no longer have uncle blocks.
Ethereum also now has Layer 2s,
whereas back then
this talk did not mention Layer 2s at all,
and now we know Layer 2s
are half the story. Ethereum is
above all an evolving ecosystem,
and these contents will keep
changing as the technology changes
and as the ecosystem's focus
shifts from building basic
infrastructure to now
putting a huge amount of focus on
applications. So what is Ethereum?
First, Ethereum is the world computer.
Who here remembers Ethereum being the
world computer?
This is where I'm supposed
to insert that meme
with the astronaut holding a gun,
saying "Always has been," but I never
understood why giving someone such an
amazing revelation should
come at the same time as
shooting them in space
20,000 kilometers away from home,
so I'm not going to do that.
Ethereum is the world computer;
it always has been and always will be.
In addition, Ethereum is an
incredibly large and diverse on-chain
economy.
Fortunately, Josh right before me
gave an excellent presentation
about all the different aspects
of that economy.
Ethereum is also an
incredibly large and diverse global
community, and Josh and the
automated intro we saw earlier
did a great job highlighting that.
Ethereum is many things.
You're probably also supposed
to flash a sign that says "ETH is money"
as well, but Ethereum is
lots of different things, and if Ethereum
is all of these things at once,
how does the world computer work?
Here's how I think about it:
Layer 1 is the trust machine,
and Layer 2 is the GPU.
Layer 1 is the core
Ethereum blockchain, the anchor
that keeps the ecosystem
safe and holds it
together. Layer 1 is why
Layer 2s can trustfully talk
to each other, and once everything
upgrades to stage two, you'll
be able to take an asset, issue it
on Optimism,
move it into a smart contract on Arbitrum,
and do so
with zero counterparty risk.
Layer 1 is not there to be ultra-fast;
it's not there to do a million transactions
per second. Layer 1 is first and foremost
there to be decentralized, robust,
and dependable.
Layer 2 is the GPU,
made up of all of you in this room who are
part of any Layer 2. Who here
is part of a Layer 2?
Great. Who here has used a Layer 2?
Who has used Layer 1?
Great, we're all users here, so
there are lots of these
different GPUs, and Ethereum the
world computer stays together
because each one of these GPUs
is connected to the trust machine
through optimistic proof systems,
zero-knowledge proofs, SNARKs, STARKs,
Boojum, PlonK, whatever the buzz
words are, and all of
these systems ensure Layer
1 can trustfully verify what is
going on inside Layer 2s, and
Layer 2s can also trustfully
read what is happening on Layer 1.
There's an important interplay between
these two components, and together they
make up the Ethereum we have today.
So what is Layer 1? It's a chain that runs
proof of stake and doesn't falter.
So what does this mean?
Ethereum Layer 1 is a chain that has
existed altogether for more than nine
years, and it has existed in its
current PoS form for a
little over two years. I think
one of the really important things for a
base layer is having
clear evidence that you're building
on something decentralized,
open, robust,
and likely to keep those traits
going into the future.
Part of that, of course, is being
something that is slow to change,
not something that will suddenly
wake up on a Tuesday
with new management that
suddenly decides it's going to
start deleting a
whole bunch of applications, change its
entire model, and push fees
up by a factor of ten
without warning. Another part of
decentralization and resilience is
recovery, so whenever a
problem starts to arise
you can recover from it and
have a way to improve the
qualities of Layer 1 over time.
Over here on the left is a
chart of Bitcoin Proof of Work mining
pools, and on the right is
Ethereum Proof of Stake validators.
I'm being generous to Bitcoin here,
because putting Bitcoin
PoW mining pools next to Ethereum
before the Merge shows that Ethereum PoW
was even more concentrated
than this, and so what
you see on the right is the spread of Ethereum PoS validators.